in the last chapter you and i started to step through the internal workings of a transformer
this is one of the key pieces of technology inside large language models and a lot of other tools in the modern wave of ai
lava it first hit the scene in a now famous twenty seventeen paper called attention is all you need
and in this chapter you and i will dig into what this attention mechanism is
visualizing how it processes data
as a quick recap
here's the important context i want you to have in mind
the goal of the model that you and i are studying is to take in a piece of text and predict what word comes next
the input text is broken up into little pieces that we call tokens
and these are very often words or pieces of words
but just to make the examples in this video easier for you and me to think about
let's simplify by pretending that tokens are always just words
the first step in a transformer is to associate each token with a high dimensional vector what we call its embedding
now the most important idea i want you to have in mind is how directions in this high dimensional space of all possible embeddings can correspond with semantic meaning
in the last chapter we saw an example for how direction can correspond to gender in the sense that adding a certain step
in this space can take you from the embedding of a masculine noun to the embedding of the corresponding feminine noun
that's just one example
you could imagine how many other directions in this high dimensional space could correspond to numerous other aspects of a word's meaning
the aim of a transformer is to progressively adjust these embeddings so that they don't merely encode an individual word but instead they bake in some much much richer contextual meaning
i should say at front that a lot of people find the attention mechanism this key piece in a transformer very confusing
so don't worry if it takes some time for things to sink in
i think that before we dive into the computational details and all the matrix multiplications
it's worth thinking about a couple examples for the kind of behavior that we want attention to enable
consider the phrases American true mole
one mole of carbon dioxide
and take a biopsy of the mole
you and i know that the word mole has different meanings in each one of these
based on the context
but after the first step of a transformer the one that breaks up the text and associates each token with a vector the vector that's associated with mole
would be the same in all three of these cases because this initial token embedding is effectively a lookup table with no reference to the context
it's only in the next step of the transformer that the surrounding embeddings have the chance to pass information into this one
the picture you might have in mind is that there are multiple distinct directions in this embedding space
encoding the multiple distinct meanings of the word mole
and that a well trained attention block calculates what you need to add to the generic embedding to move it to one of these more specific directions as a function of the context
to take another example
consider the embedding of the word tower
this is presumably some very generic
non specific direction in the space associated with lots of other large tall nouns
if this word was immediately preceded by Eiffel
you could imagine wanting the mechanism to update this vector so that it points in a direction that more specifically
encodes the Eiffel tower maybe correlated with vectors associated with Paris and France and things made of steel
if it was also preceded by the word miniature
then the vector should be updated even further so that it no longer correlates with large tall things
more generally than just refining the meaning of a word
the attention block allows the model to move information encoded in one embedding to that of another
potentially ones that are quite far away
and potentially with information that's much richer than just a single word
what we saw in the last chapter was how after all of the vectors flow through the network including many different attention blocks the
computation that you perform to produce a prediction of the next token is entirely a function of the last vector in the sequence
so imagine for example that the text you input is most of an entire mystery novel all the way up to a point near the end which reads therefore the murderer was
if the model's going to accurately predict the next word
that final vector in the sequence
which began its life simply embedding the word was
will have to have been updated by all of the attention blocks to represent much much more than any individual word
somehow encoding all of the information from the full context window that's relevant to predicting the next word
to step through the computations though
let's take a much simpler example
imagine that the input includes the phrase a fluffy blue creature roamed the verdant forest
and for the moment
suppose that the only type of update that we care about is having the adjectives adjust the meanings of their corresponding nouns
what i'm about to describe is what we would call a single head of attention
and later we will see how the attention block consists of many different heads run in parallel
again the initial embedding for each word is some high dimensional vector that only encodes the meaning of that particular word with no context
actually that's not quite true
they also encode the position of the word
there's a lot more to say about the specific way that positions are encoded
but right now
all you need to know is that the entries of this vector are enough to tell you both what the word is and where it exists in the context
let's go ahead and denote these embeddings with the letter e
the goal is to have a series of computations produce a new refined set of embeddings where for example those corresponding to the nouns have ingested the meaning from their corresponding adjectives
and playing the deep learning game
we want most of the computations involved to look like matrix vector products
where the matrices are full of tunable weights
things that the model will learn based on data
to be clear i'm making up this example of adjectives updating nouns just to illustrate the type of behavior that you could imagine an intention had doing
as with so much deep learning
the true behavior is much harder to parse
because it's based on tweaking and tuning a huge number of parameters to minimize some cost function
it's just that as we step through all of the different matrices filled with parameters that are involved in this process
i think it's really helpful to have an imagined example of something that it could be doing to help keep it all more concrete
for the first step of this process
you might imagine each noun like creature asking the question hey
are there any adjectives sitting in front of me
and for the words fluffy and blue to each be able to answer yeah
i'm an adjective and i'm in that position
that question is somehow encoded as yet another vector
another list of numbers
which we call the query for this word
this query vector though has a much smaller dimension than the embedding vector say one hundred and twenty eight
computing this query looks like taking a certain Matrix which i'll label wq and multiplying it by the embedding
compressing things a bit let's write that query vector as q and then any time you see me put a Matrix next to an arrow like this one
it's meant to represent that multiplying this Matrix by the Vector at the Arrow's start gives you the Vector at the Arrow's end
in this case you multiply this matrix by all of the embeddings in the context producing one query vector for each token
the entries of this matrix are parameters of the model
which means the true behavior is learned from data
and in practice what this matrix does in a particular attention head is challenging to parse
but for our sake
imagining an example that we might hope that it would learn
we'll suppose that this query Matrix maps the embeddings of nouns to certain directions in this smaller query space that somehow encodes the notion of looking for adjectives in preceding positions
as to what it does to other embeddings who knows
maybe it simultaneously tries to accomplish some other goal with those
right now we're laser focused on the nouns
at the same time associated with this is a second Matrix called the key Matrix which you also multiply by every one of the embeddings
this produces a second sequence of vectors that we call the keys
conceptually you want to think of the keys as potentially answering the queries
this key Matrix is also full of tunable parameters
and just like the query Matrix
it maps the embedding vectors to that same smaller dimensional space
you think of the keys as matching the queries whenever they closely align with each other
in our example
you would imagine that the key Matrix maps the adjectives like fluffy and blue to vectors that are closely aligned with the query produced by the word creature
to measure how well each key matches each query
you compute a dot product between each possible key-query pair
i like to visualize a grid full of a bunch of dots
where the bigger dots correspond to the larger dot products
the places where the keys and queries align
for our adjective noun example that would look a little more like this where if the keys produced by fluffy and blue really do
align closely with the query produced by creature then the dot products in these two spots would be some large positive numbers
in the Lingo machine learning people would say that this means the embeddings of fluffy and blue attend to the embedding of creature
by contrast the dot product between the key for some other word like the and the query for creature would be some small or negative value that reflects that these are unrelated to each other
so we have this grid of values that can be any real number from negative infinity to infinity
giving us a score for how relevant each word is to updating the meaning of every other word
the way we're about to use these scores is to take a certain weighted sum along each column
weighted by the relevance
so instead of having values range from negative infinity to infinity
what we want is for the numbers in these columns to be between zero and one
and for each column to add up to one
as if they were a probability distribution
if you're coming in from the last chapter
you know what we need to do then
we compute a Softmax along each one of these columns to normalize the values
in our picture
after you apply Softmax to all of the columns
we'll fill in the grid with these normalized values
at this point
you're safe to think about each column as giving weights according to how relevant the word on the left is to the corresponding value at the top
we call this grid an attention pattern
1 now if you look at the original transformer paper
there's a really compact way that they write this all down
here the variables q and k represent the full arrays of query and key vectors respectively
those little vectors you get by multiplying the embeddings by the query and the key matrices
this expression up in the numerator is a really compact way to represent the grid of all possible dot products between pairs of keys and queries
a small technical detail that i didn't mention is that for numerical stability it happens to be helpful to divide all of these values by the square root of the dimension in that key query space
then this Softmax that's wrapped around the full expression is meant to be understood to apply column by column
as to that v term
we'll talk about it in just a second
before that there's one other technical detail that so far i've skipped
during the training process
when you run this model on a given text example
and all of the weights are slightly adjusted and tuned to either reward or punish it
based on how high a probability it assigns to the true next word in the passage
it turns out to make the whole training process a lot more efficient if you simultaneously have it predict every possible next token following each initial subsequence of tokens in this passage
for example with the phrase that we've been focusing on
it might also be predicting what words follow creature and what words follow the
this is really nice because it means what would otherwise be a single training example effectively acts as many
for the purposes of our attention pattern
it means that you never want to allow later words to influence earlier words
since otherwise they could kind of give away the answer for what comes next
what this means is that we want all of these spots here the ones representing later tokens influencing earlier ones to somehow be forced to be zero
the simplest thing you might think to do is to set them equal to Zero
but if you did that the columns wouldn't add up to one anymore
they wouldn't be normalized
so instead a common way to do this is that before applying Softmax you set all of those entries to be negative infinity
if you do that then after applying Softmax all of those get turned into Zero but the columns stay normalized
this process is called masking
there are versions of attention where you don't apply it
but in our gpt example
even though this is more relevant during the training phase than it would be say running it as a chatbot or something like that
you do always apply this masking to prevent later tokens from influencing earlier ones
another fact that's worth reflecting on about this attention pattern is how its size is equal to the square of the context size
so this is why context size can be a really huge bottleneck for large language models and scaling it up is non trivial
as you might imagine
motivated by a desire for bigger and bigger context windows
recent years have seen some variations to the attention mechanism aimed at making context more scalable
but right here
you and i are staying focused on the basics
OK great
computing this pattern lets the model deduce which words are relevant to which other words
now you need to actually update the embeddings
allowing words to pass information to whichever other words they're relevant to
for example you want the embedding of fluffy to somehow cause a change to creature that moves it to a different part of this twelve thousand dimensional embedding space that more specifically encodes a fluffy creature
what i'm going to do here is first show you the most straightforward way that you could do this
though there's a slight way that this gets modified in the context of multi headed attention
this most straightforward way would be to use a third Matrix
what we call the value Matrix
which you multiply by the embedding of that first word
for example fluffy
the result of this is what you would call a value vector
and this is something that you add to the embedding of the second word
in this case something you add to the embedding of creature
so this value vector lives in the same very high dimensional space as the embeddings
when you multiply this value matrix by the embedding of a word
you might think of it as saying
if this word is relevant to adjusting the meaning of something else
what exactly should be added to the embedding of that something else in order to reflect this
looking back in our diagram
let's set aside all of the keys and the queries
since after you compute the attention pattern
you're done with those
then you're going to take this value matrix and multiply it by every one of those embeddings to produce a sequence of value vectors
you might think of these value vectors as being kind of associated with the corresponding keys
for each column in this diagram
you multiply each of the value vectors by the corresponding weight in that column
for example here under the embedding of creature you would be adding large proportions of the value vectors for fluffy and blue while all of the other value vectors get zeroed out or at least nearly zeroed out
and then finally
the way to actually update the embedding associated with this column
previously encoding some context free meaning of creature
you add together all of these rescaled values in the column
producing a change that you want to add that all labeled delta e
and then you add that to the original embedding
hopefully what results is a more refined vector encoding the more contextually rich meaning like that of a fluffy blue creature
and of course you don't just do this to one embedding you apply the same weighted sum across all of the columns in this picture producing a sequence of
changes adding all of those changes to the corresponding embeddings produces a full sequence of more refined embeddings popping out of the attention block
zooming out this whole process is what you would describe as a single head of attention
as i've described things so far
this process is parametrized by three distinct matrices
all filled with tunable parameters
the key the query and the value
i want to take a moment to continue what we started in the last chapter with the score keeping where we count up the total number of model parameters using the numbers from gpt three
these key and query matrices each have twelve thousand two hundred eighty eight columns matching the embedding dimension and one hundred twenty
eight rows matching the dimension of that smaller key query space this gives us an additional one point five million or so parameters for each one
if you look at that value Matrix by contrast
the way i've described things so far would suggest that it's a square Matrix that has twelve thousand two hundred eighty eight columns and twelve thousand two hundred eighty eight rows
since both its inputs and its outputs live in this very large embedding space
if true that would mean about one hundred fifty million added parameters
and to be clear
you could do that
you could devote orders of magnitude more parameters to the value map than to the key and query
but in practice
it is much more efficient if instead you make it so that the number of parameters devoted to this value map is the same as the number devoted to the key and the query
this is especially relevant in the setting of running multiple attention heads in parallel
the way this looks is that the value map is factored as a product of two smaller matrices
conceptually i would still encourage you to think about the overall linear map one with inputs and outputs both in this
larger embedding space for example taking the embedding of blue to this blueness direction that you would add to nouns
it's just that it's broken up into two separate steps
the first matrix on the right here has a smaller number of rows typically the same size as the key query space what this means is you can think of it as mapping the large embedding vectors down to a much smaller space
this is not the conventional naming
but i'm going to call this the value down Matrix
the second Matrix maps from this smaller space back up to the embedding space
producing the vectors that you use to make the actual updates
i'm going to call this one the value up Matrix
which again is not conventional
the way that you would see this written in most papers looks a little different
i'll talk about it in a minute
in my opinion
it tends to make things a little more conceptually confusing
to throw in linear algebra jargon here
what we're basically doing is constraining the overall value map to be a low rank transformation
turning back to the parameter count all four of these matrices have the same size and adding them all up we get about six point three million parameters for one attention head
as a quick side note to be a little more accurate everything described so far is what people would call a self attention head to distinguish it from a variation that comes up in other models that's called cross attention
this isn't relevant to our gpt example
but if you're curious
cross attention involves models that process two distinct types of data
like text in one language and text in another language that's part of an ongoing generation of a translation
or maybe audio input of speech and an ongoing transcription
a cross attention head looks almost identical
the only difference is that the key and query maps act on different datasets
in a model doing translation for example
the keys might come from one language while the queries come from another
and the attention pattern could describe which words from one language correspond to which words in another
1 and in this setting there would typically be no masking since there's not really any notion of later tokens affecting earlier ones
staying focused on self attention though
if you understood everything so far
and if you were to stop here
you would come away with the essence of what attention really is
all that's really left to us is to lay out the sense in which you do this many many different times
in our central example we focused on adjectives updating nouns
but of course
there are lots of different ways that context can influence the meaning of a word
if the words they crashed the preceded the word car
it has implications for the shape and the structure of that car
and a lot of associations might be less grammatical
if the word wizard is anywhere in the same passage as Harry
it suggests that this might be referring to Harry Potter
whereas if instead the words Queen Sussex and William were in that passage
then perhaps the embedding of Harry should instead be updated to refer to the Prince
for every different type of contextual updating that you might imagine
the parameters of these key and query matrices would be different to capture the different attention patterns
and the parameters of our value map would be different based on what should be added to the embeddings
and again in practice the true behavior of these maps is much more difficult to interpret where the weights are set to do whatever the model needs them to do to best accomplish its goal of predicting the next token
as i said before everything we described is a single head of attention and a full attention block inside a transformer consists
of what's called multi headed attention where you run a lot of these operations in parallel each with its own distinct key
query and value maps
GPT three for example uses ninety six attention heads inside each block
considering that each one is already a bit confusing
it's certainly a lot to hold in your head
just to spell it all out very explicitly
this means you have ninety six distinct key and query matrices producing ninety six distinct attention patterns
then each head has its own distinct value matrices used to produce ninety six sequences of value vectors these are all added together using the corresponding attention patterns as weights
what this means is that for each position in the context each token
every one of these heads produces a proposed change to be added to the embedding in that position
so what you do is you sum together all of those proposed changes
one for each head
and you add the result to the original embedding of that position
this entire sum here would be one slice of what's outputted from this multi headed attention block a single one of those refined embeddings that pops out the other end of it
again this is a lot to think about
so don't worry at all if it takes some time to sink in
the overall idea is that by running many distinct heads in parallel
you're giving the model the capacity to learn many distinct ways that context changes meaning
pulling up our running tally for parameter count with ninety six heads each including its own variation of these four matrices each block of multi headed attention ends up with around six hundred million parameters
there's one added slightly annoying thing that i should really mention for any of you who go on to read more about transformers
you remember how i said that the value map is factored out into these two distinct matrices
which i labeled as the value down and the value up matrices
the way that i framed things would suggest that you see this pair of matrices inside each attention head
and you could absolutely implement it this way
that would be a valid design
but the way that you see this written in papers and the way that it's implemented in practice looks a little different
all of these value up matrices for each head appear stapled together in one giant Matrix that we call the output Matrix associated with the entire multi headed attention block
and when you see people refer to the value matrix for a given attention head
they're typically only referring to this first step
the one that i was labeling as the value down projection into the smaller space
for the curious among you i've left an on screen note about it it's one of those details that runs the risk of distracting
from the main conceptual points but i do want to call it out just so that you know if you read about this in other sources
setting aside all the technical nuances
in the preview from the last chapter
we saw how data flowing through a transformer doesn't just flow through a single attention block
for one thing
it also goes through these other operations called multi layer perceptrons
we'll talk more about those in the next chapter
and then it repeatedly goes through many many copies of both of these operations
what this means is that after a given word imbibes some of its context
there are many more chances for this more nuanced embedding to be influenced by its more nuanced surroundings
the further down the network you go
with each embedding taking in more and more meaning from all the other embeddings
which themselves are getting more and more nuanced
the hope is that there's the capacity to encode higher level and more abstract ideas about a given input beyond just descriptors and grammatical structure
things like sentiment and tone
and whether it's a poem
and what underlying scientific truths are relevant to the piece
and things like that
turning back one more time to our scorekeeping gpt three includes ninety six distinct layers
so the total number of key
query and value parameters is multiplied by another ninety six
which brings the total sum to just under fifty eight billion distinct parameters devoted to all of the attention heads
that is a lot to be sure
but it's only about a third of the hundred seventy five billion that are in the network in total
so even though attention gets all of the attention
the majority of parameters come from the blocks sitting in between these steps
in the next chapter
you and i will talk more about those other blocks
and also a lot more about the training process
a big part of the story for the success of the attention mechanism is not so much any specific kind of behavior that it enables
but the fact that it's extremely parallelizable
meaning that you can run a huge number of computations in a short time using GPUs
given that one of the big lessons about deep learning in the last decade or two has been that scale alone seems to give huge qualitative improvements in model performance
there's a huge advantage to parallelizable architectures that let you do this
if you want to learn more about this stuff i've left lots of links in the description
in particular anything produced by Andre Karpathy or Chris Olah tend to be pure gold
in this video i wanted to just jump into attention in its current form
but if you're curious about more of the history for how we got here and how you might reinvent this idea for yourself
my friend vivek just put up a couple videos giving a lot more of that motivation
also britt cruise from the channel the art of the problem has a really nice video about the history of large language models
in the last chapter you and i started to step through the internal workings of a transformer
this is one of the key pieces of technology inside large language models and a lot of other tools in the modern wave of ai
lava it first hit the scene in a now famous twenty seventeen paper called attention is all you need
and in this chapter you and i will dig into what this attention mechanism is
visualizing how it processes data
as a quick recap
here's the important context i want you to have in mind
the goal of the model that you and i are studying is to take in a piece of text and predict what word comes next
the input text is broken up into little pieces that we call tokens
and these are very often words or pieces of words
but just to make the examples in this video easier for you and me to think about
let's simplify by pretending that tokens are always just words
the first step in a transformer is to associate each token with a high dimensional vector what we call its embedding
now the most important idea i want you to have in mind is how directions in this high dimensional space of all possible embeddings can correspond with semantic meaning
in the last chapter we saw an example for how direction can correspond to gender in the sense that adding a certain step
in this space can take you from the embedding of a masculine noun to the embedding of the corresponding feminine noun
that's just one example
you could imagine how many other directions in this high dimensional space could correspond to numerous other aspects of a word's meaning
the aim of a transformer is to progressively adjust these embeddings so that they don't merely encode an individual word but instead they bake in some much much richer contextual meaning
i should say at front that a lot of people find the attention mechanism this key piece in a transformer very confusing
so don't worry if it takes some time for things to sink in
i think that before we dive into the computational details and all the matrix multiplications
it's worth thinking about a couple examples for the kind of behavior that we want attention to enable
consider the phrases American true mole
one mole of carbon dioxide
and take a biopsy of the mole
you and i know that the word mole has different meanings in each one of these
based on the context
but after the first step of a transformer the one that breaks up the text and associates each token with a vector the vector that's associated with mole
would be the same in all three of these cases because this initial token embedding is effectively a lookup table with no reference to the context
it's only in the next step of the transformer that the surrounding embeddings have the chance to pass information into this one
the picture you might have in mind is that there are multiple distinct directions in this embedding space
encoding the multiple distinct meanings of the word mole
and that a well trained attention block calculates what you need to add to the generic embedding to move it to one of these more specific directions as a function of the context
to take another example
consider the embedding of the word tower
this is presumably some very generic
non specific direction in the space associated with lots of other large tall nouns
if this word was immediately preceded by Eiffel
you could imagine wanting the mechanism to update this vector so that it points in a direction that more specifically
encodes the Eiffel tower maybe correlated with vectors associated with Paris and France and things made of steel
if it was also preceded by the word miniature
then the vector should be updated even further so that it no longer correlates with large tall things
more generally than just refining the meaning of a word
the attention block allows the model to move information encoded in one embedding to that of another
potentially ones that are quite far away
and potentially with information that's much richer than just a single word
what we saw in the last chapter was how after all of the vectors flow through the network including many different attention blocks the
computation that you perform to produce a prediction of the next token is entirely a function of the last vector in the sequence
so imagine for example that the text you input is most of an entire mystery novel all the way up to a point near the end which reads therefore the murderer was
if the model's going to accurately predict the next word
that final vector in the sequence
which began its life simply embedding the word was
will have to have been updated by all of the attention blocks to represent much much more than any individual word
somehow encoding all of the information from the full context window that's relevant to predicting the next word
to step through the computations though
let's take a much simpler example
imagine that the input includes the phrase a fluffy blue creature roamed the verdant forest
and for the moment
suppose that the only type of update that we care about is having the adjectives adjust the meanings of their corresponding nouns
what i'm about to describe is what we would call a single head of attention
and later we will see how the attention block consists of many different heads run in parallel
again the initial embedding for each word is some high dimensional vector that only encodes the meaning of that particular word with no context
actually that's not quite true
they also encode the position of the word
there's a lot more to say about the specific way that positions are encoded
but right now
all you need to know is that the entries of this vector are enough to tell you both what the word is and where it exists in the context
let's go ahead and denote these embeddings with the letter e
the goal is to have a series of computations produce a new refined set of embeddings where for example those corresponding to the nouns have ingested the meaning from their corresponding adjectives
and playing the deep learning game
we want most of the computations involved to look like matrix vector products
where the matrices are full of tunable weights
things that the model will learn based on data
to be clear i'm making up this example of adjectives updating nouns just to illustrate the type of behavior that you could imagine an intention had doing
as with so much deep learning
the true behavior is much harder to parse
because it's based on tweaking and tuning a huge number of parameters to minimize some cost function
it's just that as we step through all of the different matrices filled with parameters that are involved in this process
i think it's really helpful to have an imagined example of something that it could be doing to help keep it all more concrete
for the first step of this process
you might imagine each noun like creature asking the question hey
are there any adjectives sitting in front of me
and for the words fluffy and blue to each be able to answer yeah
i'm an adjective and i'm in that position
that question is somehow encoded as yet another vector
another list of numbers
which we call the query for this word
this query vector though has a much smaller dimension than the embedding vector say one hundred and twenty eight
computing this query looks like taking a certain Matrix which i'll label wq and multiplying it by the embedding
compressing things a bit let's write that query vector as q and then any time you see me put a Matrix next to an arrow like this one
it's meant to represent that multiplying this Matrix by the Vector at the Arrow's start gives you the Vector at the Arrow's end
in this case you multiply this matrix by all of the embeddings in the context producing one query vector for each token
the entries of this matrix are parameters of the model
which means the true behavior is learned from data
and in practice what this matrix does in a particular attention head is challenging to parse
but for our sake
imagining an example that we might hope that it would learn
we'll suppose that this query Matrix maps the embeddings of nouns to certain directions in this smaller query space that somehow encodes the notion of looking for adjectives in preceding positions
as to what it does to other embeddings who knows
maybe it simultaneously tries to accomplish some other goal with those
right now we're laser focused on the nouns
at the same time associated with this is a second Matrix called the key Matrix which you also multiply by every one of the embeddings
this produces a second sequence of vectors that we call the keys
conceptually you want to think of the keys as potentially answering the queries
this key Matrix is also full of tunable parameters
and just like the query Matrix
it maps the embedding vectors to that same smaller dimensional space
you think of the keys as matching the queries whenever they closely align with each other
in our example
you would imagine that the key Matrix maps the adjectives like fluffy and blue to vectors that are closely aligned with the query produced by the word creature
to measure how well each key matches each query
you compute a dot product between each possible key-query pair
i like to visualize a grid full of a bunch of dots
where the bigger dots correspond to the larger dot products
the places where the keys and queries align
for our adjective noun example that would look a little more like this where if the keys produced by fluffy and blue really do
align closely with the query produced by creature then the dot products in these two spots would be some large positive numbers
in the Lingo machine learning people would say that this means the embeddings of fluffy and blue attend to the embedding of creature
by contrast the dot product between the key for some other word like the and the query for creature would be some small or negative value that reflects that these are unrelated to each other
so we have this grid of values that can be any real number from negative infinity to infinity
giving us a score for how relevant each word is to updating the meaning of every other word
the way we're about to use these scores is to take a certain weighted sum along each column
weighted by the relevance
so instead of having values range from negative infinity to infinity
what we want is for the numbers in these columns to be between zero and one
and for each column to add up to one
as if they were a probability distribution
如果你从最后一章开始
你知道我们需要做什么
我们沿着这些列中的每一列计算一个Softmax以规范化值
在我们的照片里
将Softmax应用于所有列后
我们将用这些归一化值填充网格
在这一点上
您可以安全地将每列视为根据左侧单词与顶部对应值的相关性来赋予权重
我们称这个网格为注意力模式
1现在如果您查看原始变压器纸
他们有一种非常紧凑的方式把这些都写下来
这里变量q和k分别代表查询向量和键向量的完整数组
你通过将嵌入乘以查询和键矩阵得到的那些小向量
分子中的这个表达式是一种非常紧凑的方式来表示键对和查询之间所有可能点积的网格
我没有提到的一个小技术细节是，为了数值稳定性，将所有这些值除以该关键查询空间中维度的平方根恰好有助于
那么这个包裹在完整表达式周围的Softmax应该被理解为逐列应用
至于那个v项
我们一会儿再谈
在那之前还有一个技术细节我已经跳过了
在培训过程中
当您在给定的文本示例上运行此模型时
所有的重量都被稍微调整和调整以奖励或惩罚它
基于它分配给文章中真正的下一个单词的概率有多高
事实证明，如果您同时让它预测本文中每个初始标记子序列之后的每个可能的下一个标记，则整个训练过程会更加高效
例如我们一直关注的短语
它也可能预测哪些单词跟随生物，哪些单词跟随
这真的很好，因为它意味着否则将是一个单一的训练示例有效地充当许多
就我们的注意力模式而言
这意味着你永远不想让后面的词影响前面的词
否则他们可能会泄露接下来会发生什么的答案
这意味着我们希望这里所有的这些点，那些代表后来的代币影响早期代币的点，以某种方式被迫为零
你可能认为最简单的事情是将它们设置为零
但是如果你这样做了，列加起来就不再是一个了。
它们不会正常化
因此，一种常见的方法是在应用Softmax之前将所有这些条目设置为负无穷大
如果你这样做，那么在应用Softmax后，所有这些都变成了零，但列保持标准化
这个过程称为掩蔽
有些版本的注意力你不应用它
但在我们的gpt示例中
尽管这在训练阶段比将其作为聊天机器人或类似的东西运行更相关
您确实始终应用此掩码以防止以后的令牌影响以前的令牌
关于这个注意力模式另一个值得反思的事实是它的大小如何等于上下文大小的平方
这就是为什么上下文大小可能是大型语言模型的一个非常巨大的瓶颈，并且扩大它的规模并非易事
正如你可能想象的那样
出于对越来越大的上下文窗口的渴望
近年来，注意力机制出现了一些变化，旨在使上下文更具可扩展性
但就在这里
你和我专注于基础
好的，太棒了。
计算这个模式可以让模型推断出哪些单词与哪些其他单词相关
现在您需要实际更新嵌入
允许单词将信息传递给与它们相关的任何其他单词
例如，你希望蓬松的嵌入以某种方式导致生物的变化，将其移动到这个一万二千维嵌入空间的不同部分，更具体地编码蓬松的生物
我在这里要做的是首先向您展示最直接的方法
尽管在多头注意力的情况下，这种情况会有轻微的改变
最直接的方法是使用第三个矩阵
我们称之为价值矩阵
乘以第一个词的嵌入
例如蓬松
这样做的结果就是你所说的值向量
这是你添加到第二个单词嵌入中的东西
在这种情况下，您添加到生物嵌入中的东西
所以这个值向量与嵌入位于同一个非常高维的空间中
当您将此值矩阵乘以单词的嵌入时
你可能会认为这是在说
如果这个词与调整其他事物的含义有关
为了反映这一点，应该在嵌入其他东西时添加什么？
回顾我们的图表
让我们抛开所有的密钥和查询
因为在你计算了注意力模式之后
你受够那些了
然后你要把这个值矩阵乘以每一个嵌入，产生一系列值向量
您可能会认为这些值向量与相应的键相关联
对于此图中的每一列
您将每个值向量乘以该列中的相应权重
例如，在生物嵌入下，您将为蓬松和蓝色添加大比例的值向量，而所有其他值向量都被归零或至少接近归零
然后最后
实际更新与此列关联的嵌入的方法
先前编码了一些与上下文无关的生物含义
您将列中所有这些重新缩放的值相加
产生一个您想要添加的更改，所有标记为delta e
然后你把它添加到原始嵌入中
希望结果是一个更精致的向量，编码更丰富的上下文含义，就像蓬松的蓝色生物一样
当然，你不只是对一个嵌入这样做，你在这张图片中的所有列上应用相同的加权和，产生一系列
将所有这些更改添加到相应嵌入的更改会产生一系列更精细的嵌入，从注意力块中弹出
缩小整个过程就是你所描述的单一注意力
正如我迄今为止所描述的那样
这个过程由三个不同的矩阵参数化
都充满了可调参数
查询的键和值
我想花点时间继续我们在最后一章开始的分数保持，我们使用gpt 3中的数字计算模型参数的总数
这些键和查询矩阵各有一万二千二百八十八列匹配嵌入维度和一百二十
八行匹配较小键查询空间的维度，这为我们提供了每个额外的一百五十万左右的参数
如果你对比一下矩阵的值
到目前为止，我描述事情的方式表明它是一个方形矩阵，有一万二千二百八十八列和一万二千二百八十八行
因为它的输入和输出都存在于这个非常大的嵌入空间中
如果为真，那将意味着增加大约一亿五千万个参数
说清楚
你可以这么做
您可以将更多数量级的参数用于值映射而不是键和查询
但实际上
相反，如果您使专用于此值映射的参数数量与专用于键和查询的数量相同，则效率会高得多
这在并行运行多个注意力头的设置中尤其重要
这看起来是价值映射被分解为两个较小矩阵的乘积
从概念上讲，我仍然鼓励您考虑具有输入和输出的整体线性映射
更大的嵌入空间，例如将蓝色嵌入到您要添加到名词中的蓝色方向
只是它被分成了两个独立的步骤
右边的第一个矩阵具有较少数量的行，通常与键查询空间大小相同，这意味着您可以将其视为将大型嵌入向量映射到更小的空间
这不是传统的命名
但我要称之为向下取值矩阵
第二个矩阵从这个较小的空间映射回嵌入空间
生成用于进行实际更新的向量
我将把这个称为价值向上矩阵
这也不是传统的
你在大多数报纸上看到的方式看起来有点不同。
我一会儿再说
依我看
这往往会让事情在概念上更加混乱
在这里加入线性代数行话
我们基本上做的是将整体价值图限制为低秩转换
回到参数计数，所有四个矩阵都有相同的大小，把它们加起来，我们得到一个注意力头大约有630万个参数。
作为一个快速的侧面说明，为了更准确一点，到目前为止描述的一切都是人们所说的自我注意头，以将其与其他模型中出现的称为交叉注意的变化区分开来
这与我们的gpt示例无关
但如果你好奇的话
交叉注意力涉及处理两种不同类型数据的模型
就像一种语言的文本和另一种语言的文本一样，这是正在进行的翻译生成的一部分
或者语音的音频输入和正在进行的转录
交叉注意力头看起来几乎一模一样
唯一的区别是键和查询映射作用于不同的数据集
例如，在模型中进行翻译
密钥可能来自一种语言而查询来自另一种语言
注意力模式可以描述一种语言中的哪些单词对应另一种语言中的哪些单词
1，在这种情况下，通常不会有掩蔽，因为没有任何后来的代币影响早期代币的概念
保持专注于自我关注
如果你理解到目前为止的一切
如果你在这里停下来
你就会明白注意力的本质
真正留给我们的是阐明你多次这样做的感觉
在我们的中心示例中，我们专注于形容词更新名词
但是当然
有很多不同的方式可以影响一个词的意思
如果他们撞坏了这个词在汽车这个词之前
它对那辆车的形状和结构有影响
很多联想可能不太符合语法。
如果巫师这个词和哈利出现在同一段中
这表明这可能是指哈利波特
然而，如果苏塞克斯女王和威廉这两个词出现在这段文字中
那么也许哈利的嵌入应该更新为指王子
对于你可能想象到的每一种不同类型的上下文更新
这些键矩阵和查询矩阵的参数将不同以捕获不同的注意力模式
根据应该添加到嵌入中的内容，我们的值图的参数会有所不同
同样，在实践中，这些地图的真实行为更难解释权重设置在哪里，以做模型需要它们做的任何事情，以最好地实现预测下一个标记的目标
正如我之前所说，我们描述的一切都是一个注意力头，变压器内的一个完整注意力块由
这就是所谓的多头注意力，你可以并行运行很多这样的操作，每个操作都有自己独特的键。
查询和价值图
例如，GPT 3在每个块内使用96个注意力头
考虑到每一个都已经有点混乱了
你脑子里肯定有很多东西
只是为了非常清楚地说明这一切
这意味着您有96个不同的键和查询矩阵，产生96种不同的注意力模式
然后每个头都有自己独特的价值矩阵，用于产生96个价值向量序列，这些都是使用相应的注意力模式作为权重添加在一起的
这意味着对于上下文中的每个位置，每个标记
这些头中的每一个都会产生一个建议的更改，以添加到该位置的嵌入中
所以你要做的就是把所有这些提议的改变加在一起
每个头一个
您将结果添加到该位置的原始嵌入中
这里的整个总和将是从这个多头注意力块输出的一部分，从它的另一端弹出的那些精致嵌入中的一个
同样，这需要考虑很多事情。
所以如果需要一些时间来理解，请不要担心。
总体想法是通过并行运行许多不同的头
你让这个模型有能力学习很多不同的方式来理解上下文改变意义。
拉起我们的参数计数的运行记录，每个有96个头，包括这四个矩阵的自己的变化，每个多头注意力块最终有大约6亿个参数
还有一件有点烦人的事情，我真的应该提一下，如果你们继续阅读更多关于变压器的文章的话。
你还记得我说过价值图被分解成这两个不同的矩阵吗？
我将其标记为向下值和向上值矩阵
我构建事物的方式表明你在每个注意力头中看到这对矩阵
你完全可以这样实现它
那将是一个有效的设计
但是你在报纸上看到的方式和在实践中实现的方式看起来有点不同。
每个头的所有这些值上升矩阵都被钉在一个巨大的矩阵中，我们称之为与整个多头注意力块相关的输出矩阵
当你看到人们参考给定注意力的价值矩阵时
他们通常只提到第一步
我标记为向下投影到较小空间的值
对于你们中好奇的人来说，我在屏幕上留下了一张纸条，这是有分散注意力风险的细节之一。
从主要的概念观点来看，但我确实想把它说出来，这样你就知道如果你在其他来源中读到这一点
抛开所有的技术细微差别
在上一章的预览中
我们看到数据在转换器中的流动不仅仅是通过一个注意力块。
一方面
它还通过称为多层感知器的其他操作
我们将在下一章中详细讨论这些
然后它反复地经历这两个操作的许多许多副本
这意味着在一个给定的单词吸收了它的一些上下文之后
这种更微妙的嵌入有更多的机会受到其更微妙的环境的影响
你走得越远
随着每个嵌入从所有其他嵌入中获得越来越多的意义
它们本身变得越来越微妙
希望有能力对给定输入的更高层次和更抽象的想法进行编码，而不仅仅是描述符和语法结构
比如情绪和语气
不管是一首诗
以及哪些潜在的科学真理与这篇文章相关
诸如此类的事情
再回到我们的记分gpt三包括96个不同的层
所以键的总数
查询和值参数再乘以九十六
这使得总和接近580亿个不同的参数专用于所有的注意力头
这是一个很大的肯定
但这只占整个网络中750亿人口的三分之一。
所以即使注意力得到了所有的关注
大多数参数来自于这些步骤之间的块
在下一章
你和我会更多地谈论其他街区
还有更多关于培训过程的信息
注意力机制之所以成功，很大一部分原因并不在于它能促成某种特定的行为。
但事实是它非常可并行
这意味着您可以使用GPU在短时间内运行大量计算
鉴于在过去的一二十年里关于深度学习的一个重要教训是仅规模似乎就能在模型性能方面带来巨大的质量改进
让您执行此操作的可并行化架构具有巨大优势
如果你想了解更多关于这些东西的信息，我在描述中留下了很多链接。
特别是安德烈·卡尔帕西或克里斯·奥拉生产的任何东西都倾向于纯金
在这个视频中，我想以当前的形式引起人们的注意
但是如果你想知道更多关于我们是如何到达这里的历史，以及你如何为自己重新发明这个想法
我的朋友vivek刚刚发布了几个视频，给了我更多的动力。
另外，来自问题的艺术频道的Britt crus有一个关于大型语言模型历史的非常好的视频